thank you for oh sorry
hello and welcome it is February 9th
were in octave guest stream number 36.1
with ballot Ben Fallen days so Ben thank
you for joining
we're gonna have a presentation and then
a discussion period so thanks again for
joining looking forward to your
presentation
yeah thanks so much for having me I'm
really excited to uh connect with the
active inference community on this stuff
so hopefully some people are in the live
stream and uh can we can have some
discussion at the end of this so I'm
going to talk about this recent
pre-print that we dropped um with my
collaborators Jeff Yoshimi Bill Warren
and Michael Spivey titles right there so
I'll just jump into it
so the backdrop that we're thinking
about when we came up with this paper
um was that most cognitive scientists
think that cognition is about mental
representations and most of them think
that those mental representations are
constituted by brain Dynamics or in
philosophy jarging you might say
supervene on brain Dynamics
um and so hopefully that's not a very
controversial statement
and what we're trying to do in this work
is take one step towards a
non-representational account of the
central nervous system meaning the brain
and kind of connected parts of the
central nervous system
um so why should we want to do this
what's the what's the problem with
representations so I'm just going to
present a sample of four problems these
are not uh this is not a comprehensive
view of what could be wrong with
representations but these are some
things that might encourage you to look
for an alternative
the first one is that just because you
have some encoding or a correspondence
between internal mental activity and
something out in the world doesn't get
you to content to meaning of the
representations and that is basically
getting at something that's called the
symbol grounding problem I'll talk about
in a second
beyond that we can note that in central
nervous system activity there's a high
degree of context dependence even down
to the tunings of individual neurons so
given a different task or a different
setting you see what look like different
encodings appearing so that seems like
it would be a problem if you're actually
trying to use that for an encoding so
you have to keep track of how those
encodings are changing according to the
context
uh the third problem I'm going to
mention is a recent finding in the
Neuroscience literature it's called
representational Drift and the point
here is that when you see what looks
like encodings in the brain if you look
over long enough time scales and and
these are not actually very long time
scales maybe even a day or a couple of
days you find that those encodings move
around in the brain
so again if if they were to be used by
the brain as an encoding it not only has
to keep track of what is the mapping but
how is the mapping changing over time
that's a problem because the system that
needs to keep track of how it's changing
is also the thing that's changing so
it's not clear to me if that could even
work or what kind of uh you know
computational mechanism you'd need to
make that work
and the fourth thing is the argument
that we just don't need representations
at least for a lot of tasks so this is a
major point in the ecological and
embodied literature is that a lot of the
you know major problems that organisms
are trying to solve appear solvable
without using any uh you know complex
internal representations
so I'll just briefly give you an example
of each of these the first one I'm going
to rely on this really nice 2019 paper
from Romaine Bretta
um I apologize if I'm pronouncing his
name incorrectly
um
and uh one example that that he shows in
this paper is we imagine a scenario in
which a neuroscientist is doing a single
cell recording of the tuning of a visual
neuron
and they're varying uh wavelengths right
so they're varying colors presenting
various colors and you're seeing which
color elicits the greatest response from
this neuron so we've got wavelength on
the x-axis and the output or the current
coming from that neuron on the y-axis
and what these gray lines are showing
are different intensities
so the point here is that the output of
the neuron is not just a function of
wavelength it's also a function of
intensity so that means that you can get
the same output with uh multiple
different combinations of wavelength and
intensity so you could have kind of high
intensity low wavelength or you know
medium intensity medium wavelength and
so forth
so if you're a neuroscientist who's
holding intensity constant in this
context then you might read that
activity as a mapping but the point here
is that the brain doesn't know that the
neuroscientist is holding that constant
even if you tell someone there's no way
for the brain to look outside itself and
see that that mapping holds
now somebody you know might point out
that
um actually neuroscientists don't
typically think that single neurons are
encoding wavelength but they might say
that they're relative response of
multiple neurons is encoding it so on
this uh plot B we've got two different
neurons with different tunings and you
present it with some wavelength and they
have different responses and that might
carry intensity invariant information so
that's helpful
um but what I want to emphasize here is
that wavelength and intensity are just
uh two properties that might emerge from
a stimulus of which there could be many
more that we don't know of so it's only
by virtue of knowing that
um that the response of the neuron
doesn't vary according to these other
properties that you can actually call it
a code and that's something that the
brain can never do is figure out what
other things could this neuron respond
to
so this is kind of a neuroscience
framing on What's called the symbol
grounding problem a lot of cognitive
scientists might be familiar with the
Chinese room thought experiment the idea
here is that a person is locked inside a
room all their exchange with the outside
world are messages that are passed
through the door that come in in Chinese
and the person inside the room doesn't
speak Chinese but they have a book that
translates from one set of symbols to
another and so they get a message in
they translate it and they pass a
message out and to the person on the
outside of the room it looks like
there's a native or fluent Chinese
speaker inside the room but of course
the person doesn't know any Chinese so
what this is trying to point out is that
if all you have are mappings from
symbols to symbols you can never figure
out what the meaning of those symbols
are
and this is the simple grounding problem
I think it's kind of a fatal
um problem for any representational view
with all the buzz around chat GPT and
stuff like that people are you know
having debates over whether or not it
could be sentient this is something that
comes up a lot is that really all it has
are these relations between tokens and
at the end of the day it doesn't know
what it's talking about it doesn't have
meaning and for me and and many others
uh I think that grounding your symbols
or at least being able to avoid this
problem somehow is crucial for
understanding Consciousness or
subjective experience so arguably if you
have a representational view you might
run into problems
um naturalizing subjective experience
and consciousness
second problem I mentioned is that
Central Nervous System activity can be
context dependent so here I'm going to
show an example that comes from Gilbert
and Lee 2013 top down influences on
visual processing what they did is have
chimps I believe
um do uh task switching Paradigm so what
you're seeing on the right
is a setup where there's a square in the
middle and it's got a line inside the
square and there are lines on the right
and left and also on the top and bottom
and so at various times the chimp is
going to be paying attention to some
task that's going vertically or they
might do another task that's going
horizontally and they're they're
supposed to ignore what's happening on
the other side and what they looked at
was the tuning to orientation of
individual neurons in this case
so what they found is that depending on
whether the line was presently task
relevant or task irrelevant you get a
different response from the same neuron
to the same line so it seems like it
doesn't even have a fixed uh kind of
tuning or preference for any orientation
but it's going to depend on the task
again it once it becomes context
dependent then you need a way to keep
track of the context but you get into
this infinite regress where the brain
just can't step outside itself to figure
out what the context is
the third problem
um pretty recent finding in the last
couple years uh this idea of
representational drift and this is
starting to be demonstrated in more and
more uh studies and I expect there will
just be a flood of these coming the idea
is that you know we've thought for a
long time that the brain can Implement
certain uh kind of correspondences that
look like topological encodings for
example spatial encodings
so in this classic task they had a rat
doing a t maze so it moves down the
length of this T and then goes towards
reward they trained the rat got it to
master this maze
and they record the activity and so
first I'll direct you to just this top
left panel and what we're looking at on
the x-axis are different locations
within the maze so uh this is designated
as Q offset so basically how far away
from the reward
and then on the y-axis we've got
different cells and they're sorted
according to their response to
particular locations and so what we see
in this first panel is that as the rat
moves along the maze you see this nice
kind of topographical encoding that
there's a series of cells that are
responding across the length of this T
Maze and it looks like there's a spatial
mapping inside the brain
but if you look at those same cells on
day 10 you can see that that uh that
spatial mapping has totally faded and by
day 20 it's it's completely gone and on
day 10 you have a totally different set
of cells that are implementing that
spatial mapping so it's some distributed
mapping in the brain but it's moving
around over time
this has now been demonstrated in
primary visual cortex primary olfactory
cortex so these are low level sensory
systems that presumably everything
higher up is going to rely on and so uh
you know reading the responses of
neuroscientists this are they seem kind
of shocked the question is how could you
have an encoding system that's based on
a foundation that is constantly shifting
and the final point that I want to make
is that for a lot of cases we might just
not need uh representations and this is
a big uh emphasis with an ecological
psychology and embodied cognition
and so I'm going to mention an example
that is probably the most used example
in those fields which is the outfielder
problem and the idea is that there's a
baseball player they view a ball that's
just been you know hit or launched in
some way and they have to try to run to
the landing location and catch the ball
if you're a representationalist or you
know kind of a classical cognitive
science approach to this you might
assume that the the uh baseball player
first looks at the ball and they
calculate some predicted trajectory of
the ball that gives them a predicted
Landing location and then they run to
that location so there's a lot of kind
of internal machinery and
representations happening
while the alternative is that uh the the
baseball player can just run so as to
keep the ball constant in their visual
field and that's a little bit of a
simplification of what it is but
essentially if you move so that the ball
stays it's a kind of
um acceleration left or right and your
retina stays stable you're just going to
end up where it ends up and so the idea
here is that you visually couple to
properties of the ball and you can get
the job done without needing to have any
internal representations that you're
reading
so we use the ecological framing in in
this paper so I'll tell you a little bit
more about the background and the kind
of literature that we were trying to
engage
with this and uh the some some jargon to
introduce is that the gibsonian or
ecological psychology view says that
what organisms perceive are not uh you
know objects it's not the environment
it's affordances and affordances means
opportunities for Action so a chair
affords sitting stairs a forward
climbing and what you see are those
potentialities for interaction or what
you perceive I should say
how do you perceive those well the idea
is that those are specified in
ecological information so there's
structured uh energy in the environment
and that energy can be revealed through
relationships between action and
perception so for example if you're
swaying a little bit to the left and
right you're kind of changing your angle
of view on some objects and that's going
to reveal depth cues how far away is the
object from you
so what I want to emphasize here is that
there Gibson was trying to point out
that the environment is actually rich
with information
um as opposed to the standard view that
sensory systems have impoverished
information so if you think that there's
not enough information in the
environment then it makes sense that
you'd have to do all these internal
calculations and inferences to figure
out what's out there if you think that
the environment is Rich with information
then maybe you can just skip all of that
stuff
so uh affordances are specified by
ecological information and uh when you
detect ecological information Gibson
says that you're resonating to it
so what does it mean to resonate so he's
kind of using this example that's uh
related to these two tuning Forks over
here the idea is if you have two tuning
Forks that are the same resonant
frequency which means the kind of
natural frequency at which they're going
to vibrate and you strike tuning fork a
then those sound waves will travel out
and cause tuning fork B to resonate
so I think what Gibson is pointing to
here is that this kind of coupling of
organisms to affordances is uh is a
direct physical coupling
um and not an inferential coupling
and Gibson described learning as
Attunement
um so
uh one thing I want to point out here is
that in order for two tuning Forks or
resonate to each other they have to have
the same resonant frequency so if one is
bigger than the other thicker different
material it might have a different
resonant frequency and if you strike
tuning fork a it might not cause tuning
fork B to resonate but what you can do
is change the properties of tuning fork
b a little bit you could put a damper on
it or you know other
methods for altering the resonant
frequency such that it's going to couple
with tuning fork a so that's his idea
about learning is that we're actually
just kind of gradually refining our
perceptual system until we just happen
to resonate to useful information in the
environment
so what's the what's the mechanism of
this how does this happen
um what what Vicente Raja and colleagues
have pointed out recently is that
resonance remains a metaphor so Gibson
you know described this idea but he
doesn't give a mechanism if we want a
mechanism we probably need to look in
the central nervous system
right so it's not just that any type of
system can do this it requires a certain
type of system
um you know a slug for example can't uh
go catch a fly ball right it's not going
to be able to resonate to that
information so that might be a bad
example but the point is that we want to
know what are the specifics of the
system that allow it to change its its
resonance properties and ultimately pick
up useful information in the environment
ecological psychology is really focused
on this level of the organism
environment relationship and that's a
purposeful thing because they're trying
to emphasize that often we don't really
need to uh look at brain activity to get
a more or less complete understanding we
can get really far just at this top
level
without appealing to this lower level
information but eventually we want to
get there so that's what we're trying to
take a step towards in this work
one model that I think is useful in this
domain is the reservoir computer
so some some cognitive scientists have
pointed out that Reservoir computers are
interesting as a model of cognition in
general because they give you these
three properties that we might want from
a cognitive system
um and actually first I should explain
what the architecture of these systems
are so we have a little diagram of a
simple
um you know example of a reservoir
computer the idea is that there's some
input layer that has feed forward
connections to a reservoir so this is
just a collection of nodes that are
connected together with random sparse
connectivity
and that gives it the property of not
having stable attractors so if you give
it some input then the input is just
going to kind of propagate through that
network over time
um and then it feeds forward to an
output layer and usually they also have
a connection from the input directly to
the output so what's cool about these
one is that it gives you dynamic memory
so the idea is that when you project an
input when you give an input to this
Reservoir what it's essentially doing is
taking a low dimensional signal and
projecting it into a high dimensional
space so that allows you to separate
information from a lot of time scales
but also have it be interacting
constantly so you can have things that
are changing on slower time scales for
example interacting immediately with uh
faster time scales but the network is
kind of setting up a context for itself
and it's preserving all that information
across time
um and so I kind of hit on both the
dynamic memory and the time scale
integration also if you have multiple
inputs to this network like multiple you
know sensory modalities it's gonna
automatically integrate those things
um and I should take a step back to to
hit a point that I missed about the
dynamic memory is that
in the kind of flow through this network
it is implicitly preserving a trace of
the history of inputs
and so this to to understand this you
can think of the kind of inspiration of
reservoir networks which is an actual
pool of water so if you're throwing
rocks into a pool of water it's going to
create some pattern of ripples on the
water
and as you throw more rocks in those
ripples are going to start to interact
with each other and if you have a way to
read those ripples then at any given
time slice you can figure out the
history of rocks hitting that Network so
the history of perturbations so some
long memories kind of preserved in the
Rippling pattern here
another thing that's cool about these is
that they're computationally efficient
because you just need to train a linear
readout mapping so you don't have to
have any complex back propagation the
weights in the network don't usually
update and you can train multiple
readouts at the same time so you can
have one input to the network and you
can have multiple parallel computations
being performed on that
um so this is cool for for ecological
psychology but one problem with it is
that it's still pretty representational
right so you're training a readout
mapping uh we we you know requires an
observer that's gonna suffer from the
simple grounding problem
and it's not very biologically realistic
in the way that real neurons do so the
neurons are not updating inside the
reservoir in any way the weights aren't
changing we know that actual brains are
are very dynamic
so what are neurons if they're not if
we're not going to think of them as you
know vehicles of representation
primarily they're just living organisms
so this is the focus that I tried to
take here is thinking of the neuron
first as an agent that's just trying to
survive and that the properties of
brains and the properties of the
collective actually emerge from these
individual level mechanisms
what are some of those mechanisms so I'm
going to call these mechanisms of
homeostasis meaning self-maintenance so
neurons trying to stay within some
viable space of of input
um to point out before I begin this if
neurons don't have any input they're
going to die so they need some input
they actually compete with each other
for inputs they're kind of putting out
uh tendrils and trying to form
connections and the ones that get good
connections are gonna survive ones that
don't get enough connections are going
to die but also if you have too much
input it's a bad thing so you can get
something called excitotoxicity which is
a neuron is basically going to explode
and and die because it has too much
input
so what can they do to deal with this
one thing is to adjust intrinsic
parameters so these are things like the
leak or pump rate the number or location
of receptors and there's lots of kind of
Gene regulatory processes going on where
they might be turning on or off
different genes in order to change their
local parameters
and I want to point out that although
this is homeostatic that can change the
set point right so if you keep input
constant a neuron can either increase or
decrease its its receptivity to that
input it could have you know more
receptors or less receptors and that can
change the level of input that it
prefers
um it can also adjust extrinsic
parameters so forming new synapses
adjusting synaptic weights and there's
Global synaptic scaling as well so
there's this
um relatively recently discovered
phenomenon where
a neuron can scale the total amount of
input so it's basically changing all of
its synapses at once
and in this view
um this is a little bit of speculation
on my part but if we're thinking of
neurons as agents then what is spiking I
argue that it might be a resource
management method first and in that
sense the way to dissipate too much
energy dissipate energy quickly when a
neuron has too much input
and then that function that kind of
survival function could be co-opted for
cooperation or for signaling so how does
this work if you imagine that one neuron
is overloaded and it's just going to
dissipate a bunch of energy well that
energy is basically wasted but if some
other neuron is connected to it then it
can use that waste to keep itself within
its own bounds so it sets up the
possibility for these kind of resource
sharing functions
at the same time you could think of that
as as carrying a signaling function if
you know that uh you know your neighbor
has hit hard times and is kind of
selling all of their uh you know
Furniture then that might be a signal
that there's some economic problem
coming down the line so it implicitly
functions as a signal that some
perturbation has occurred that your
neighbor was not prepared for
the hypothesis here is that from those
low-level processes those neural level
regulation processes you get Global
behavioral control of the entire
organism so what is the argument here
first proposition is that
homeostatic mechanisms are going to
regulate that flow of energy through a
network so they're trying to distribute
resources in the most efficient way so
that all of the neurons can thrive
you can't regulate the flow through a
network very well unless you control the
flow into a network so if you have a
constant input stream then you can learn
how to distribute that in a nice pattern
of flow that works for the network but
if the input stream is constantly
changing different neurons are getting
perturbed at different times then it
creates a challenge for that problem
um
I also want to point out that the flow
into the network is driven both By
changes in the environment and by the
organism itself so if an organism's in
an environment if they stay still the
environment can change and that might
create different inputs to the network
at the same time whatever the network is
doing is going to potentially cause some
motor movement some action and so you
might you know the organism might turn
and look at something else and that's
also going to change the flow into the
network and usually both of these things
some combination of them are happening
simultaneously
so how do you solve this problem well
you can't get a homeostatic equilibrium
in this network
unless you stabilize that higher order
relationship so you have to have some
kind of regular pattern of uh organism
environment relations in order to have a
regulated flow of input to the network
so that's why we think that if you just
put homeostatic mechanisms into
individual neurons then this Global
property of the collective uh being kind
of adaptive organism is going to emerge
so I'll tell you about how I tried to
formalize these ideas
um and I'll direct you first to the top
left these are the possible states of
the neurons so each neuron that I
modeled had some activation level that's
represented by these purple bars and
Daniels can you see my cursor here or do
I need to put on a pointer
I think maybe it's there okay cool so
each neuron has some activation level
and we assume that there's a floor a
minimum
activation that it can have
and uh there's also a Target activity
level so this is just your homeostatic
set point but I want to point out that
that Target is going to vary so we don't
put that in on our own we initialize it
but we let the neurons decide what
Target they want
and that Target also has a minimum value
the reason for that is that we assume
that neurons need at least some level of
input so you can't have a Target that is
zero where a neuron prefers to not get
any input ever it needs to prefer to at
least get some input but it might prefer
to get a lot of input or it might prefer
to get a little
and then there's a firing threshold and
when the neuron goes over that firing
threshold it's going to spike
So based on these possible states that
neurons can find themselves in we've got
a set of rules and that's this flow
chart that I just had at the bottom here
the idea is that if you are under your
target so in the top left then the way
to get closer to your target is either
to recruit more input or to try to lower
your target if it's not at the floor so
you're kind of trying to converge those
two parameters so that you can get to a
stable equilibrium
um if your activation level is over the
target but under the threshold then you
can do the reverse you can try to
decrease the amount of input you get or
you can try to raise your Target and
actually they're doing both here
then you get the case where the neuron
is over the Target and they're over the
spiking threshold so what they're going
to do is dissipate all of the stored
energy and end up with just the
remainder so in this case this neuron
was just slightly over its threshold and
so what's going to be left after spiking
is just this red section at the top
it'll end up being below its Target
that creates an interesting kind of
heavy-in mechanism where if you spike
and you end up below your target then
you actually need to recruit more input
to get back to your to your target so
you might increase the weights with
nodes that just cause you to spike so
out of purely homeostatic mechanisms we
get these kind of learning properties
that emerge
so here's the basic architecture of the
model and in the gray box in the middle
I'm showing just the network and then on
the sides the kind of agent environment
system that we put it into so first I'll
I'll talk about the network there's some
sensory layer consisting of a number of
nodes and what these nodes are going to
do is Spike when there's a stimulus at
some egocentric location
so for example this top node might be
corresponding to your right eye and if
light hits that right eye then this top
node is going to spike if it hits the
left eye maybe this other node spikes
so we actually have an array of those
kind of representing something like a
retina where there's a series of sensors
that get triggered
and those nodes have purely feed forward
connections to the homeostatic Reservoir
these are sparse random connections that
means for us probability of of forming a
connection is ten percent so we walk
through every sensory node and give it a
10 chance of connecting with any node in
the reservoir
then the reservoir consists of a
relatively larger number of nodes that
Implement that homeostatic mechanism
that I just described
just to clarify the sensory and effector
layer are not homeostatic
so this Reservoir layer also has
recurrent connections that are directed
they're not bi-directional
and again we just use this sparse random
connectivity there's no spatial
structure built into the network for now
so you know this neuron can connect to
the neuron in the top right just as well
as the one that I have pictured right
next to it
and then finally we have a form same
process to form connections with some
effector layer and in all of the
examples that I show here the effector
layer is two nodes
and what each of those nodes are going
to do is normalize their input so that
it is going to take on some value
between 0 and 1 for each of these two
nodes
and then that's going to drive motor
output so you might imagine that the top
node makes you turn left the bottom node
makes you turn right
if you're fully activating the top node
and not activating the bottom node then
you just completely turn left
full amounts of activation then you stay
still it's balanced
so that's the general idea
and then we put it in some environment
where there's a stimulus that's going to
perturb that sensory layer that stimulus
can move around and does in in the first
couple of cases that I'll show
and then motor output is going to change
the position or orientation of the
network
so again I want to point out that this
has that kind of action perception
feedback loop where the input to the
network could change either because the
stimulus changes or because the motor
output causes the network to orient
itself differently or some combination
of the two of those
so I'll show you four case studies of
what we did with this and the first
thing I'll show is the the original
paper that I put this model in which was
in a language processing context
and then I'll show three more from this
most recent pre-print where we have it
in an action perception context
processing stuff
um some background
the first thing is that a lot of
language researchers especially in the
last decade or so have started to think
that the brain is a prediction machine
why do we think that well AI models do
very well being trained on next word
prediction you know this is the uh
essentially the basis of a lot of modern
um uh large language models like chat
GPT although it gets a little more
complicated in those so that they're
predicting upcoming signals and getting
some error signal that leads to learning
and in some cases the activity of those
networks looks a lot like what humans
are doing
a ton more uh examples that I could cite
of of evidence that people point to for
why it looks like we might be predicting
this is just kind of one larger point
but there are at least two ways that you
might understand what that means
on the left one is that brains might be
predictive coding machines and that
means that actually the signals that are
propagating through the brain are
prediction errors
um and what that prediction what the
hypothesis I should say of of this is
that you'll get a reduction in Signal
when you have predictable or expected
inputs and you get a spike in Signal
when you have unpredictable inputs
but there's another view that's related
which is uh sometimes described as
predictive processing which is maybe a
weaker version of this which is that you
can get that prediction-like behavior
you can get those same behavioral
signatures without specifically relying
on explicit prediction mechanisms so you
don't necessarily need to have nodes
that make uh predictions or that
propagate prediction errors
so what I did to get at at this issue
was take this network that I just
described except in this case it had no
output layer so it's just a passive
response uh device and I used 100 nodes
the input layer was five nodes and those
uh nodes were one hot encodings of five
distinct words that I'll show you in a
second and those were this is going to
generate a sequence of inputs that come
from a probabilistic grammar
so what does that mean here are our five
possible inputs uh man walks dog
and bytes and space
so those are our five possible inputs
and we create some probability of
transitions so a sentence might start
with man the most likely flow is that
it'll say man walks dog and it always
ends with a space and then you come back
to the beginning
this is going to generate a series of
probabilities of different observations
the most probable are either man walks
dog at the top here or dog bites man and
the least probable are man bites dog or
dog walks man and you get multiple other
combinations
so what I want to point out here is that
this gives you a simple system simple
kind of environment you could think of
it that way a linguistic environment
that has statistical structure to it but
it's not fully deterministic right
there's some Randomness and probability
built in
so what I'm showing on the left are the
spike patterns for the reservoir Network
at the end of exposing this network to
about a thousand of these sentences
and so each column here is contains all
the nodes in the network and each row is
a Time step corresponding to an input
position and if that node was spiking we
have it in yellow and if it was silent
at that time we have it in blue
so you see that we're getting a series
of inputs man walks dog dog bites man
man walks dog and then what we do is
present it with a kind of uh prompt one
input to start a sentence like man and
then we don't give it any further input
and because of the properties of
reservoir networks and this dynamic
memory or what you could call fading
memory
the activity of the network keeps going
at least for a few time steps so it's
going to generate some series of outputs
even though it's not getting any input
and what we wanted to ask is do those
generated outputs resemble uh reasonable
patterns does it look like the network
is kind of generating predictions of the
next word
one way to get at this is looking at the
correlations between Spike patterns
so what we have here is time on the
x-axis and the y-axis and we're showing
the the correlation between all of these
points and
um kind of on the bottom right here
these are the places where there was no
input and so this section is actually
the the bounded section here by the
dotted line is what we're interested in
is how
uh how similar were these outputs when
there was no input to previous outputs
when there was input
um and just to point out some kind of
clear cases up at the top here I'll look
at this Center column where it got the
word man and if you go back in time and
you find there's a high correlation what
was it correlated with that was a
previous instance where it saw a man so
it seems like the network generates
something that looks like a pseudo
population code and I'll tell you in a
second why we call them pseudo but it
has a kind of pattern that represents or
corresponds to each word so it seems so
to make this a little more clear I'll
just show you like what was the highest
correlation which we'll call the
prediction of the network and I have it
in scare quotes because we're using that
Loosely for now
so if we give it an input of man and we
cut off the network it predicts or it
creates some output that is most highly
correlated with previous instances of
the word walks
and of course this is the most likely
next input if we give it man walks and
then cut off the input the output
resembles dog
and this goes down the line so in each
case
um when you cut off the input the output
looks mostly like what you'd expect if
you had continued the input so it's kind
of like it's dreaming the next
um set of inputs and this might look
like it's predicting or doing sentence
completion
so we looked for some some behavioral
signatures of what's often taken as
evidence of predictive coding
um and the other thing that I mentioned
was an increase of activity in the
network for unlikely inputs so what we
have on x-axis on the left here is the
transitional probability so How likely
was that switch
and what you can see is that as the
transitional probability goes up the
mean activity goes down so that means
that the more surprising the input the
higher the activity of the network so
this looks like it might be kind of
having a uh it looks like it's Error
coding right so it's got a large error
signal when it gets a surprising input
another way that we got at this was
giving it a bunch of training
um trials with the standard uh
transitional probability Matrix
and so we are showing
um the last 100 iterations of training
where it's going subject verb object
space subject verb object blah blah blah
and it's kind of nicely oscillating in
some level of activity
and then we suddenly switch the order
instead of giving it subject verb object
we give it subject object verb and you
see a huge spike in activity so it
doesn't like to get those things that
are out of order so it seems like not
only is it kind of classifying
um the possible inputs it's also
learning something about the temporal
structure in the transitional
probability Matrix
when we look at the correlations another
thing I just quickly want to point out
is that the activity can differentiate
the same input at two different
positions right so you can get man as a
subject of a sentence or as an object of
a sentence and you see different
response patterns in those cases
so that's not built into the network it
gets the same input so it seems like it
knows something about the position
and it's also showing similarities
between different input words that are
in the same class so man and dog are the
nouns walks and bytes are the verbs and
when we see correlations between these
so we'll see that
for example
bytes has a 0.28 correlation with uh
with walks
and that doesn't seem very high but if
you look at the rest of the correlations
they're you know near zero except for
the ones that we're interested in here
so that's the language stuff that that
kind of spurred this and then we wanted
to ask if this model was going to
generalize to other tasks so in that
language example models just passively
receiving inputs well what's going to
happen if we give it an output layer
where whatever goes on in the network
can also potentially change the next
input
and we looked at three Asian environment
systems just to see you know how well
does this generalize to a variety of
cases
and the first thing that I tried
um was an agent that is fixed at a
center point and they just rotate so
they can't move just rotate and there's
a stimulus that it's going to rotate
around the agent and sometimes it's
going to change directions
we give this agent two eyes
um that are 30 degrees apart those eyes
have an array of sensors that correspond
to different egocentric angles the idea
is that this is again like a retina so
there's one you know sensor that's going
to be straight ahead if something's
right in front of you and if something's
off to the side then it hits you at a
different angle different sensor is
going to respond to that
we also gave it two effectors
um which we just arbitrarily dub one as
the left turn and one as the right turn
the idea is that these are like the
motor system and that there's kind of
random connectivity to for example your
left or your right leg
so I'll show you a quick video of of
what happens in the top left here is our
our agent is this pink circle
um this is intended to look kind of like
a top-down view of a head
and these red and blue dots are the two
eyes and then there's this green
stimulus that you'll see move around in
a circle
on the bottom we have the network and
all the nodes are blue when they're
silent they're going to turn yellow for
spikes
and we can also show the output of the
left and right turn effectors
on the top Center are the outputs of the
sensors so you'll see as the stimulus
moves the sensors uh activation is gonna
it's gonna move across the array of
sensors
and then top right we've got
um the in average you know aggregate
parameters of the nodes in the reservoir
so what is their mean activation is the
First Column
um then how what does there mean error
so how far on average are they from
their targets and then what is the
average Target
and then finally on the bottom right
we're showing the distribution of
weights and how those change that turns
out not much interesting happens in this
case it kind of stays as a normal
distribution
so here's a little video and I might
speed it up
and you can see that as the stimulus
moves around the first time the agent
kind of starts to move with it but it it
loses track
and same thing happens on the second run
and so we'll give it a third chance the
stimulus changes Direction
and now it suddenly kind of locks on and
is traveling with it and what you can
see is that it's kind of slowing the
rate of change across the sensors so
you'll see that as the stimulus changes
Direction it locks on again
and it's making the flow of input change
more gradually
what I want to point out is that this is
this is not an automatic consequence of
of the properties of this network so we
don't tell it to track the stimulus it
doesn't have any kind of rewards going
on there's no supervision
you can do whatever it wants and in
order to track the stimulus it needs to
find the right ratio of outputs so if
these the ratio of of left and right
effectors is going to determine how fast
it turns and in order to track it needs
to turn at the same speed as the
stimulus so that's essentially what it
does is discover that learning pattern
and it's not perfect but I'll try to
show an example where it here's a nice
example where it quickly changes
Direction with the stimulus so it
bounces here and it just flips and
follows it and you can see that when
it's kind of stably tracking there seems
to be a sort of limit cycle uh kind of
flipping between two activation patterns
in this one case but we see a few
different patterns
so let's analyze some of the outputs
here
um on the top panel what we're showing
on the y-axis is the angle in degrees of
the stimulus which is in Black
and the agent which is in red and then
time is on the x-axis
and what you can see from this is that
the red line is essentially tracking the
black line following the black line it's
not always perfect so here's an example
at the beginning where it loses track
and then connects back with the stimulus
and I've uh kind of lined this up with
the timing of the proportion of the
network that's spiking at each time
point
and so what we're looking for are these
kind of uh little perturbations these
jumps in activity what are causing those
jumps in activity
what we can see from this is that they
occur either when this the stimulus
changes directions so this kind of first
perturbation corresponds to a change of
Direction
or when the agent loses track of the
stimulus and then finds it again so this
next one is a case where it had lost the
stimulus and then when it comes back
around you get this burst of activity
um and it starts to track again
we can also look at the autocorrelation
of the network activity over time which
is again mapped on to this time so we've
got a time going to the right and also
downward so this is symmetrical
and what you can see is that every time
you get one of these spikes the network
shifts into a new regime so it's got
some pattern of activity that's highly
autocorrelated for a short period of
time
and then it switches to a new pattern of
activity
what's interesting about this is that
off the diagonal you don't see high
correlations right so we actually see a
lot of what look like zero or negative
correlations
and the reason this is interesting is
because the network is actually
repeating or the agent I should say is
repeating several of the same behaviors
so during this 7200 time steps it's
turning right and turning left multiple
times at the same speed and yet it seems
to be accomplishing that with a totally
different pattern of activity each time
it does it and it finds that new pattern
of activity very rapidly so it doesn't
seem to have kind of recurring encodings
that correspond to you know this is the
sub Network that turns left this is the
sub Network that turns left it finds a
totally new set of collaborators within
the network to accomplish its goals on
the Fly
all right so then uh you know I was
inspired by some recent work that uh you
acted inference folks that probably seen
um where Kagan at all grew a culture of
cortical cells on a microelectrode array
and they hooked that up to the feedback
loop of a game of pong and they found
that it uh within I think five minutes
they said it starts to improve its
performance now it didn't get very good
the performance was still just slightly
above chance but it's cool that it's
kind of self-organizing and they give
they give a you know a free energy
reading of these results
but there's no mechanism in this case
given specifically so you know what is
it about that Network that is allowing
it to minimize free energy so I wondered
if my network would do the same thing
um and I'm really curious to hear from
from anyone who's here at the end about
you know whether you think this is a
potential counter example or just a
different mechanism for for
accomplishing the same goals or is my
network also minimizing free energy
potentially so I'm not really sure yet
there's more analysis that we need to do
um but same kind of idea that this slide
is a mess but
um I just want to point out some
features of it we gave it a few more
notes 500 instead of 200 the agent in
this case is the paddle the arena is uh
500 by 1000 pixel space and the stimulus
is the pong ball and in this case the
input is encoding the relative angle of
the ball from the center of the paddle
so it's very similar to the last case
um except here instead of you know
rotating left or right the output layer
is moving the paddle up or down so what
happens when we do this so we start the
ball in the center
if the paddle misses the ball then it's
going to reset at a random position over
here
and I'll show you kind of cool hits it
on the first try but maybe not that hard
because it came right in the middle
and it's got a few uh hits it on the
third try there's some misses for sure
but you can see that it's going for it
at least which is interesting
um and yeah so just a
few examples of what it does
I guess I've shown some bad examples
where it looks pretty bad at pong but
when I show you the summary stats in a
second uh maybe that'll change your mind
about that so
um before I get to the performance
similar idea to the plot that you saw
last time is showing the
um
showing time on the x-axis and in this
case instead of the angle we have the Y
position of the ball or the center of
the paddle
and I've marked red columns where
there's a miss
and green columns where there's a hit
I just want to point out that the ball
and paddle can be at the same y position
here without contacting because they
might be at different x positions so you
know here's a case where they overlap
and there's it's not a hit or a Miss
because the ball is just not close
enough yet
so again we see this kind of spiking of
activity at certain time points what are
those time points so they seem to
correspond to Misses cases where the
paddle missed the ball and it reset and
then you get this Spike of activity and
potentially a reorganization in this
case we we don't see high
autocorrelation even along the diagonal
so it seems that the network activity is
just kind of chaotic throughout
and yet it will show in a second it
seems to have decent performance
um so here's the the performance over
500 runs in these First cases and I'll
walk you through these
first I want to point out this kind of
medium gray this is our Baseline
condition
um just you know everything that I just
described on average when there's an
opportunity to either hit or miss how
often does it hit so it's the proportion
of hits and we find that it was about 60
on average some variation uh you know
down to about 40 percent
in this case chance performance is 20
because the paddle is one-fifth the
height of the space so if the paddle
just does nothing it has a 20 chance of
hitting it so even at its worst the
network is more than twice as good as
chance
um and we wanted to see does it learn so
does performance improve over time so to
do that we we looked at just the first
50 opportunities for a hit or miss and
the last 50.
and what you can see is that there's not
much change so it seems like it's it's
you know at its Peak Performance right
away
um and maybe we're missing some learning
that happens in the time steps before
even the first hit so it could be just
kind of rapidly picking up on something
so maybe there is learning and and the
proportion of hits is too discrete of a
measure to get at that
so one other way to look at this is the
the blue column so what we did was just
turn off the homeostatic updating so
there's no learning happening in the
network
what's surprising here is that the
performance is already well above chance
so you know at its worst it's near
chance but on average it's twice as good
as chance
so why would it be doing all right if
there's no learning happening
what we hypothesized was that this is
just kind of a natural consequence of
egocentric encoding in this case the
reason for that is that if the paddle
um hits the ball then it's going to
create a predictable stream of input if
it misses it gets a maximally
unpredictive unpredictable input
um but also
due to the the
um laws of Optics the angle of the ball
to the paddle changes more rapidly as
the ball is passing the paddle so when
it's coming close to the paddle and
there's about to be a miss
that's when you get the fastest change
in input just due to trigonometry
and given a rapid change of the input
this creates a chaotic signal through
the network which means that it's going
to be more likely to generate a movement
when it's about to miss so that seems to
just automatically help it by chance to
to hit the ball even if sometimes it's
moving in the wrong direction
so to test whether that egocentric
encoding really is important we tried it
again with an allocentric encoding so
instead of encoding the angle of the
ball to the center of the paddle we just
encoded the objective y position of the
ball
and here performance is Right a chance
so it really needs that egocentric
encoding and one thing that I think is
interesting is that that Kagan at all
paper didn't use an egocentric encoding
they used an allocentric one so I'm sure
it's a lot more work to grow a culture
of cortical cells but I'd be really
curious to see if it does much better if
they give it
um an allocentric encoding
or sorry an egocentric one and so the
final case study I'll I'll talk about
um similar idea to that Kagan at all
study this came from masamori at all
2015. they also took a culture of
cortical cells put it on a
microelectrode array and used it to
control a mobile robot
and what they were wondering is does
that robot learn to avoid walls so they
put it in a in a box of some size and
just let it run around and what this is
showing is the first 15 minutes you can
see that it's kind of clustered to the
right and it's hitting the wall a bunch
of times
and last 45 minutes maybe it's you know
more in the center of the space it's not
hitting the wall so much so maybe this
network will do the same kind of thing
in that case
we went back to 200 nodes in this case
our our agent is like a bradenberg
vehicle so we simulate two wheels on
each side of the agent and the movement
is driven by the relative speed so if
you know wheel one is the right wheel is
much faster then it's just going to turn
to the left but stay still and if both
wheels are equally active it's going to
move straight forward
to our sensory system in this case is a
wall detection encoder so we have two
sensors that are just going to send
array straight out
they're going to find the distance to
the nearest wall
um and their input activity is going to
be an inverse relationship with that
distance so when it's really close to
the wall high input when it's far away
low input
I want to point out that input was
always non-zero here so we set the the
minimum activation
um to be the diagonal of the space and
so the agent actually can't get right
into the corner of the space
um so it's always going to have at least
a little bit of of input to both
effectors
or sorry both sensors
so here's our agent again now it's a you
know a little version of that first case
you saw and I'll let him run around for
a second
I think I might have given you a bad
video
uh here we go this is not the video I
intended to put in here where it's
tracing the line this might be an
earlier version but you could see that
eventually tries to find a circle
um
there we go so it finds a little circle
of movement
and I apologize that I loaded in the
wrong thing here
um
but when we in the final version of the
model that we used same setup and
basically takes a couple hundred time
steps and this agent essentially finds a
little circle that it can move in in the
middle of the space
and that has some limit cycle where the
red and blue sensors are going up and
down as it's turning around
and it needs to find a ratio of left and
right output that is going to create a
radius of a circle that keeps it within
within the walls
and so I'll jump to plots of the end
results that are a little bit better
so here's a representative run the
arrows are tracing the path that that
agent made again we've got the
proportion of the network that spiked
and then the autocorrelation
um this time with time running to the
right and up
and I put little black lines down here
for every time the agent hit the wall
so what this shows is that at the
beginning of the run it hits the wall a
bunch of times and then it uh you know
an activity is kind of chaotic and then
it finds this nice Circle in the middle
of the space and it totally stabilizes
the activity
so in this case we don't see chaotic
activity you just see this stable
pattern over time the reason for that is
that the environment is not changing in
this case
so the agent now the the inputs of the
network is changing which is interesting
but the agent has learned to compensate
for that change in input that is purely
due to its own activity so it can fully
stabilize so given that it fully
stabilized we might want to know you
know what's going to happen if it can't
find a completely stable pattern of
activity so we tried putting in some
sensory noise
so to the inputs rather than just
getting a you know a spike for that
corresponds to the distance the wall we
just add you know sampled from a uniform
distribution to add some noise to that
input signal
what you find here is largely the same
thing but it you know gets disrupted a
little bit and it starts to change the
size of the circle that it's making and
it ends up finding a smaller Circle
that's uh you know more easily
maintained Than This original Circle
given the noise and you see that you
know even though
everything else is stable in the network
you sometimes get these sudden switches
to a new pattern of activity that's
doing the same thing for the agent
then we tried something
um that was done in a kind of similar
paper
um I apologize I forget the name of the
author but we have it cited in our
preprint which is to see how the network
responds to a perturbation so what we
did here was just suddenly invert the
visual field so we switch the left and
right eyes and we did this at time 1000
what happens in this case is the network
first finds a nice Circle
and it does that for some period of time
um and then we do the visual field
inversion and it sends the agent off
track it starts crashing into the wall
again down here and then it just finds a
new Circle so in just you know under 500
time steps it fully adapts to that
inversion the visual field
and then finally we said what happens if
you if you don't have learning so in the
Palm case it seemed to work pretty well
regardless of whether or not learning
was on
in this case you don't get that same
result so if there's no learning because
the input is always non-zero the network
uh gets saturated so activity goes to a
maximum all nodes are spiking constantly
the result of that is that both output
nodes are fully active and that leads to
Straight Ahead movement so what you get
is an agent that just goes straight and
bounces off walls you'll see that it
never stops hitting the walls
activity is just peaked right away and
we can't even give an autocorrelation
Matrix here because there's no
variability in the signal
so what are our conclusions from all of
this work
um the first is that given this uh
homeostatic Network and I actually kind
of have vacillated between using
allostatic and homeostatic I guess I
forgot to change this here but I want to
point out that allostatic just means
homeostasis with a dynamic set point
um but homeostasis doesn't really uh
necessitate that the set point isn't is
static so I think it's fine to just
stick with homeostatic
um given this this homeostatic Network
we get prediction-like behavior from a
simple uh probabilistic grammar
you get spontaneous object tracking it
plays Palm uh substantially above chance
and it naturally avoids walls
all of these adaptive behaviors are
apparently adaptive behaviors
continue uninterrupted in some of these
cases even though the activity in the
network is drifting around so we don't
think that there are stable
representations in here
because the network doesn't need to use
representations it doesn't need to read
out its own activity at any point it
just needs to attune its activity to the
statistics of that agent environment
system
and if we look over just short time
slices
you do see what look like
population codes at least in the in the
language processing model so this might
give us
um you know a way of understanding why
do we often find what look like
representations or encodings in
Neuroscience studies and you know why
maybe it took so long to notice
representational drift is that we're
typically just looking over you know one
or two sessions of an individual and in
that time span you might not see these
changes
so why does this work I think that the
network is not predicting in this case
but what it's doing is
adapting but it's adapting in a kind of
counter factual or anticipatory way
so what I mean by that is that when a
node gets a perturbation
if they're you know above or below their
target what they're going to do is say
how could I change my setup so that that
would have gone differently
if that perturbation were to play back
how would I change my parameters and my
in uh you know synapses in order to
approach my target
so it does that and because these things
repeat
um you get what it looks like strong
anticipation so the network is kind of
um
generating a flow of activity by itself
that compensates for upcoming input
compensates or complements depending on
the case potentially
um so this the activity of the network
what we're arguing is not a model of the
world but it's kind of a
you know a shield for the world but it's
a kind of temporally
changing Shield it's a way to protect
itself that it's a way to protect itself
for what's coming next
and what we wrote in that original paper
to describe this is that
when an individual is successfully
adapted based on the past
and those same conditions occur again it
will look like the agent predicted those
conditions to occur it might not be that
they are literally predicting those
conditions but just that they're you
know set up for that particular
trajectory
and what we think is that just by trial
and error kind of changing parameters
um when there is a lack of homeostasis
when they're out of homeostasis
the network quickly generates what have
been called Talons so this is a term
that comes from Anderson and his
um
neural reuse work
and Talon stands for transiently active
local neuronal subsystems and I think I
switched the lowercase of the a and o
but yeah the idea is that these are you
know temporarily active neural synergies
or you know kind of Partnerships that
form on the Fly
self-organized
for their utility in a particular
context in an immediate environment
and those do not have to be read as
representational
patterns that we get there they could be
fixed point attractors they could be
limit Cycles they might even be some
some kind of strange attractor if these
networks can learn those patterns and
they're essentially just flows of
activity that uh match the flow of the
environment
as it interacts with the agent so the
flow of input is driven both by
environment and agent that creates some
pattern over time and the network
generates a complementary pattern
so the two questions I want to end on
are first the you know main question of
this paper is
does this give us a way to understand
what resonance is is this you know step
towards a mechanism or what's the best
way to think about this
and I'm really interested to hear from
you guys on how you think this this
might fit or not fit with free energy
principle and active inference so is
this system a free energy minimizing
system
how would we find out if it is or is not
if it's not a free energy minimizing
system
what does that say for for fep for you
know other approaches so I'd love to
hear your your feedback and thanks so
much to Daniel uh for having me here and
uh looking forward to the discussion
that's a wrap
awesome thank you
all right just getting back to
very cool thanks for the awesome
presentation well those who are watching
live please feel free to write a
question in the chat and I've written
down some as well let's just start with
how did you get to This research
question were you studying ecological
psychology and got interested in
modeling or were you already involved in
this kind of modeling and then wanted to
come to explore resonance
yeah great question um so I mean I'll
tell you a little bit about my kind of
path and Decor side in general which is
you know I started as a philosophy and
psych undergrad in a very kind of
traditional
cognitivist uh place and I was sort of
frustrated with both sides of those
views I thought that cognitivism had a
lot of problems so I started to learn
about embodied cognition
um and that you know I got into Andy
Clark's work that sort of uh led me into
his interest in the free energy
principle and active inference
but in the background of all these
things and kind of the motivation I
think for a lot of people
um building embodied or 40 approaches
and fep approaches is something like the
symbol grounding problem is that if we
have this problem with representations
what do we do next so that's something
that's been in the background of of all
my work sometimes more or less
explicitly
and then you know in the case of of this
model
um we were working on that that language
paper that I showed where we were
arguing that you can think of prediction
in many cases as just a kind of pattern
completion that there's some kind of
momentum of a system that flows forward
and if that momentum has become
entrained to Something in the world then
it's going to look like a prediction
um and so it just kind of based on
intuition started to make these uh
homeostatic mechanisms and see if that
would do the kind of entrainment uh that
we expected
and I was I was sort of shocked to see
that it worked right out of the box I
mean it's kind of crazy that random
sparse network no supervision
seems to do all of these tasks language
action perception
like right away so
um that was kind of amazing
awesome so
I'll give a reflection in the question
and then we'll see some questions from
chat
so I thought it was a very provocative
framing where you right at the beginning
said the neuron is the agent
and it's trying to survive in a harsh
intracranial environment and sometimes
the intracranial environment is framed
well it's dark it's warm it's chill
things are being brought to you and
if it loses oxygen for even a short
period of time the energetic rate is
such that there's damage it requires
nutrition sugar ketones whatever it may
be it is actually a survival situation
for those neurons and so by Framing at
the agent level of the neuron a
homeostatic impulse
we then see functionality arise from a
group it's like individual ants in the
colony are taking behaviors to normalize
their interaction rate and then the
colony might explore a space and if it's
a big space they'll spread out to
explore it if it's a small space they'll
slow down to explore less and so that's
a great Collective Behavior or
multi-scale systems approach which is
rather to kind of put our thumb on the
scale on the collective behavior and
then say well what what would the
neurons do
we can actually embody that lower level
agent as the one that is the action
perception cognition entity and then ask
well what does happen and as you just
put it out it's a really exciting
immersion outcome that these kinds of
brain level
homeostatic impulses arise from the
neuron level homeostatic imperative so
that's just very cool and it gives us
something to
fork or at least build off of jump off
of when we're having these discussions
about like what do neurons know what do
groups of neurons know what do organisms
know that neurons don't
and that is in some ways so core to the
representation question
yeah yeah really interesting points and
I'm glad you think this is uh this is
cool and I love that you bring up the
kind of collective intelligence Framing
and
um you know that's in the background
here for sure and another sort of stream
of my work is on cultural Evolution and
kind of emergent processes and cultural
systems that's something that I'm you
know I'm just prone to that way of
thinking and I think you're right that
you know it often looks like the brain
might be this very nice kind of
incubator for for neurons where it's set
up for for their survival but it looks
like that because they've honed these
mechanisms of collective intelligence
that something about the developmental
processes and the regulatory processes
has created an environment where they
all can can Thrive and something is
going to come out of that what I think
is interesting on an evolutionary level
is how do you get that kind of
transition into into Cooperative
Behavior what are the constraints that
lead to that
um so with a a bunch of great co-authors
or another preview print right now on
collective intelligence where we explore
some of these questions a little bit and
we look at for example a transition from
single cell dates to multicellular
States and there are some species that
can sort of suddenly do this this switch
others are obviously kind of obligatory
multicellular or always single cellular
and sometimes they can transition and so
there's you know some pressure in the
environment that triggers that
transition and eventually you might get
this kind of path dependence where they
actually end up relying on that kind of
collective structure and that gets sort
of entrenched so I think the brain is is
one of those cases and it's uh you know
really interesting to me to explore in
what ways are is the brain different
from you know human cultures or groups
of organisms and
what constraints uh you know keep us
from being a fully kind of Cooperative
hive mind which I don't think we
necessarily want but it might be
interesting still to know uh what would
shift us into those different basins
cool with a multi-cellularity and The
evolutionary origins as well as the
developmental origins of the nervous
system are in the ectoderm and the
closure of the nerve the neural tube and
so it's like you could imagine an
epithelial cell that just responds
electrochemically when it's touched and
then like you pointed out with the
neighbors selling their Furniture it's
like if this cell on the epithelium
responds well that can come to be
associated with the response from an
interior cell
without necessarily taking on this
baggage or the symbol grounding problem
all these questions of representation so
very cool I'll go to a question in the
chat anyone else can add more questions
so
Jingo writes question
wonder how this messes with
functionalist views
functionalism would say that these
systems are still functionally doing the
same things and this is just another way
of framing some other function but then
it makes you wonder whether
functionalists are cheating because the
function is only a function from our
perspective but not from the perspective
of the system slash its parts
yeah yeah and really interesting point
um
yeah so you definitely can think of
these as you know the activity of the
network is
performing a function for the collective
which is ultimately maintaining survival
in this case
but when we think of higher order
functions like turning left or or
turning right
we might read that those functions are
in there but it's hard for me to imagine
how you could say that there it you know
that that activity has a specific
function if you can't find a thing to
attach that function to
so if the function comes out of this
kind of Shifting landscape then what you
know what's the functional what's the
part that has that function can you have
a function without
the things that perform the function
um I don't know so interesting question
I'll also think more about that
cool
well let's bring it to active inference
and think about at the neuron level and
at the brain level we'll just call it
the Reservoir level think about what are
some similarities or contrasts with
active inference how would we know if
the system is
normatively described by the free energy
principle so right off the bat you
described at the neuron level a Target
set point
and that is very resonant with the
active inference framing which is that
actions are selected not based upon the
maximization of a reward or utility
function which is what we might see in
reward or reinforcement based learning
but rather an active inference actions
are selected to reduce the Divergence
between observations and preferences and
so we can talk about those preferences
as what the agent likes but also what
they expect what we expect slash prefer
like the body prefers to be at
homeostatic temperature it also expects
to find itself there it's not surprised
to find itself at homeostasis it is
surprised to find itself out of
homeostasis it takes actions to bound
surprise and then the unified imperative
that bounds surprise statistically for a
generative model is the free energy so
right off the bat what the agents are
doing in terms of reducing their
Surprise by navigating to a Target
rather than proposing a reward or
utility map
that is then climbed
but reducing surprise and reducing
Divergence between incoming observations
and an expectation slash preference is a
reward free
pattern that is just right off the bat
one of the strongest and most important
pieces that make it aligned with active
inference
yep yep yeah totally agree so you know
this is why I'm really excited to to be
here and talk with you guys because I
think there are a lot of ways in which
it's really close to active inference
and then potentially ways in which it's
it's totally Divergent
um you know little subtle differences
that might have big theoretical
consequences for how we interpret it and
so on the one hand as you say there's
this kind of Target set point which you
could cast as as a type of prediction
couple of differences I want to point
out
um
you know I I don't have much experience
with active inference modeling so I'd
love to connect with someone who does
but at least in the language processing
literature when there are predictive
coding models in particular you have to
build in a prediction mechanism so the
you know there's a flow of top-down
predictions that are changing the lower
level predictions and you're propagating
prediction errors so the question is how
how much of that framing can we expand
and you know there might be a sense in
which that kind of abstract framing is a
useful modeling approach and maybe not
an ontologically real thing that's
happening here and that could be okay
but there might be other ways in which
it just
doesn't fit at all so I think it's
possible that
um you know one thing to point out is
that
the predictions in this case uh don't
come from top down signals they're
emerging from each node
you know the the target levels
um and the way that signals are
propagated is not uh like
computationally Optimal unnecessarily
right so you might have potentially
neuron level predictions that don't get
propagated in a way that they could
potentially form higher level models of
the system so yeah I think those are
some of the the Divergence points that
I'd like to see if you know I'm I'm
wondering in particular we were to
approach this system like an organism
that we you know are studying a species
in the lab what kind of analyzes would
we do to find out if it is or is not uh
minimizing free energy and presumably
there's some set of systems we could say
these are
these are doing that others that are not
and in this case it I could imagine
scenarios in which the
flow of energy that creates a uh kind of
thriving environment for these neurons
is just a chaotic signal of some kind
that is doesn't have you know a
non-equilibrium steady state for example
it might have shifting Markov blankets
now we can say there's there's a sensory
layer there's an active layer there's
internal States
but if we if all we have is the
statistical structure of the network
then it might look like for any given
subset that there's a a changing Markov
blanket and you know maybe that
introduces problems or maybe not
cool well definitely the input sent
State internal cognition and output
action layer is something that neural
networks of certain forms have active
inference agents and really just
classically cybernetic agents so that
kind of input cognition output model and
embedding action perception loops around
that kind of an agent is something that
really
connects all of these models and then
it's a super interesting question okay
view from the outside let's test
different models and it's a point that's
been brought up and is very fascinating
to think about which is that in some
ways active inference never fails as an
analysis framework like a linear
regression never fails as an analysis
framework you could have any two
variables any scatter plot you'll always
be able to use some squares to fit a
linear regression with a smooth
optimization
you know your computer program is not
going to complain and similarly we can
always use octave inference to make a
generative model in that generative
model will always be able to minimize
its free energy and the model won't
complain now is it an adequate model is
it the best model is it a profitable
business is it an Adaptive organism I
mean no to any of them so active
inference will never complain
by being used as a view from the outside
but that doesn't mean that it's
necessarily the most computationally
effective or ontologically supported
View From the Inside the actual
mechanism and I think we see it right
here there might be a plurality of
mechanisms that lead to Resonance and
the fact that you've shown one is like
poking one hole in the veil but that
doesn't mean that's the only mechanism
that leads to Resonance because we know
that there's a plurality of cognitive
mechanisms and a diversity of life forms
that do it differently in different
niches
yep yep yeah I think that's exactly
right and you you know you raise the
interesting point that it's you can you
can always apply that modeling framework
to any system so
then that leads to the question of what
what would distinguish different kinds
of of uh you know energy minimizing
systems like an energy well stability
just a rock rolling down a hill
is minimizing thermodynamic free energy
um but it's but it's not a cognitive
system right it's not forming a model of
the environment clearly or maybe you
know there might be people who disagree
with that even but
um I don't think that Iraq is you know
forming an internal model of the system
so that leads me to think that there
should be some way to tell like how how
much Credence do we or how much you know
concrete reality do we want to attribute
to the idea of active inference in
different cases there might be some
systems that we think are literally
active inference systems and others that
we think are just you know a model and
maybe the maybe the model itself can
tell us something about that maybe we
can say like this system you know if we
model it using free energy principle we
find that it's doing a poor job or I
don't know or maybe in this case there
might be you know mathematical
properties of this system that just make
it not fit so if there isn't a
non-equilibrium steady state
in this network can can you even apply
the framework
right yeah a lot of fun directions I'll
return to a question in the chat from
Donna Raj hi Ben really cool work I'm
wondering how and where your Dynamic
homeostatic allostatic points come from
is this target externally set or emerges
from the Dynamics itself
yep yeah great question because I really
want to emphasize this point that the
the set points emerge from the Dynamics
we do initialize them
uh you know we ended up using just a
uniform initialization everything starts
at the floor
I tried it other ways and it was robust
to those to those changes so it doesn't
seem to care how you initialize it
and I think the reason that this is an
important point is that if you build in
the homeostatic set points you kind of
fall for a lot of the same problems that
I was bringing up at the beginning
related to symbol grounding so this was
you know you know cybernetic School
looked at homeostatic mechanisms and how
they can give rise to Adaptive Behavior
but there are some criticisms coming
from the ecological sphere that are
pointing out that if you're building in
those set points from the perspective of
the researcher
then you still have a problem
um so we wanted those set points to be
emergent
and uh I you know on the basis of of how
they're emergent I'm still not really
sure how to think about what is being
controlled in this case
um because you know we might say the
target's being controlled but at first
you might say you know inputs being
controlled
but because the target can change the
input can change you might say that
spiking activity is being controlled but
that can you know that can vary as well
while the neuron is still just as happy
so it might be spiking all the time and
using those spikes to get back to its
set point it could set a really you know
if one neuron is like always getting a
flood of input then it might uh try to
you know lower all of its connections
and then it's sort of adapted for a
really high level of input and so it has
a really high Target
so I'm not even really sure what is
being controlled at the individual level
and if you look at the individual nodes
they have different kind of emergent
behavioral profiles some of them are
never spiking because they are just
riding activity near their targets they
never go above their threshold
some of them are spiking on every
iteration because they've actually come
to rely on the spikes for getting back
to their threshold so they depend on you
know I'm gonna get flood of input but I
can dissipate most of that and end up
right back in my target
and they end up using that repeatedly so
you get this range of different profiles
which makes it sort of mysterious to me
and I need to do some more thinking but
yeah to just drive it home they are
emergent set points
yes very interesting well the title of
the paper a potential mechanism for
gibsonian resonance so could you speak a
little bit who is Gibson how has this
topic
of perception and action been approached
from the Gibson lineages what are some
of the key features of a gibsonian
approach and how would we know it when
we see it what are we looking for in
terms of evidence or is this a
philosophical debate and the evidence is
already on the table we're just
composing it differently is there some
data set that people are waiting to see
before they support or reject the
gibsonian perspective
yeah great great question so
um first uh James and Eleanor Gibson uh
were the founders of the ecological
school of thought and
um you know I'm not much of a historian
on Gibson so I might give some of the
details wrong here but I I know that
Gibson had a big focus on visual
perception at least early on and did
some work for for the military like
figuring out how fighter pilots were uh
you know how to set up a kind of
um
uh I don't know what I wanted to say
human computer interaction but I guess
it's not human computer interaction but
you know like a control setup how would
we design that space given what kind of
information is available to an
individual
um and so he he came up with this idea
of optic flow
um and I think the big emphasis on optic
flow is that rather than just thinking
about static images
um we're thinking about the change over
time in input to the retina so the optic
flow is the pattern of change as you're
moving around through the world
the if you start from the the idea of
static inference or sorry static images
that's kind of the classical cognitivist
approach then you think well there's not
enough information in the static image
like if I give you just a picture you
can't really uh read out the you know
all of the depth cues and and other
information from that picture so the
idea is that you need to add some
background knowledge to that and make
inferences about what's the actual
structure
but what Gibson was trying to emphasize
is that we're not dealing with static
images as an organism you're you know
moving through an environment and
certain information is revealed just you
know through that relationship between
perception and action that as I walk I'm
changing the pattern of optic flow and
there might be some structure to the
change in optic flow not just structure
in the static image
um so that leads to the you know
gibsonian approach and and it's been
expanded Way Beyond Vision
um and kind of influence the embodied
cognition or 4E approach and a lot of
people in that uh Camp are are trying to
emphasize how far you can get without
any internal representations so in
addition to you know patterns of optic
flow there's work like the kind of
passive walking machines that show that
if you just have a system with the right
kind of coupling of degrees of freedom
you can get uh like a wooden robots that
just walk with no controller whatsoever
um so their argument in a lot of cases
is that we don't need internal
representations to mediate interaction
you just need to couple with the
environment in the right kind of way and
discover what that coupling is
um and so I think you know Gibson what
we're trying to emphasize in the paper
and uh integrating it with this existing
literature is that
Gibson and the early ecological
psychologists were trying to shift away
the emphasis from internal States so
they purposely took that off the table
they said let's just look at the
relationship between the organism and
the environment and look for some higher
order stability in that system
um so for that reason resonance has has
stayed as a metaphor he never spelled
out you know what is the underlying
system that accomplishes that goal so
that's what we're trying to do now is
um move into that space and figure out
what is it about brains that makes them
resonate
very
interesting
one active angle on that
so in active inference we commonly use
What's called the particular partition
let's call that because it's one
specific way of doing it but also what
it does is it carves out particles that
are like the agent and that includes
their blanket states and their internal
States now there may be some
agents whose behavior is fully described
by the blanket so I'm thinking of a
guitar string the Resonance of the
guitar string may be
even simpler than like an input Black
Box output it's like the black box is
empty
everything about the input and output
are happening on that Markov blanket
layer there's no need to appeal to some
kind of internal state so you don't even
approach the Cliff of representation
but let's say we had two guitar strings
and we find that one we can fit a
statistical model that explains all the
variants in Behavior
with just the blanket States and so we
say this is
basically non-cognitive surely a pan
cognitivist pan computationalist could
take a different angle but whatever it
is that it's doing it's all on the
blanket it's all on the holograph in
contrast we have the second guitar
string and it's like wait a minute
there's there's something else happening
like across trials
there's some residual that we're not
modeling based upon observable input and
output so what would we do in the
Bayesian causal modeling setting we
appeal to a latent cause of action that
might look like planning or might look
like anticipation and so we can propose
cognitive models with more and more
complexity and this work it's kind of
like digging for gold or I don't know if
it's digging up for something because
it's actually showing that
tasks or cognitive functions
that previously may have been studied
from a turing machine symbol computation
perspective that might be one way to do
it in certain systems but it's not
necessary and so then the question is
going to be well what are the limits of
what interfaces can do
which is very related to the question
what are the limits of how we can model
interfaces because whenever we have a
shortcoming in our modeling
we appeal to another latent factor
so there might be some exciting things
that today we do model with cognitive
States like memory but as you brought up
with Reservoir Direction
memory can also be understood
as being kind of carried in the Dynamics
and the interfaces of collectives not
necessarily stored in a register like
you would do it on a hard drive
yep yep yeah great points and so you
know as you were saying that I realized
that I didn't fully answer every part of
your previous question which was about
what kind of data would tell you about
the difference between these two things
and
there you know at least two types that
we might look at and one is sort of
proof of concept data which is
um you know take it get a system where
you know the ground truth and you can
show that a task could be done without
any internal representations so that's
like the passive Walker machines or
um you know I think like this model is
that we can look at this and know that
there's no uh prediction mechanism
happening although maybe you can read
homeostasis in that way
um the other is I think you can give
they're you know not in every case is it
really obvious but sometimes you can
find cases where the prediction or
cognitivist approach
um versus the ecological approach are
going to make very different predictions
or at least discriminable predictions
about Behavior so for for one you know I
mentioned um
the outfielder problem and I had a paper
up there which was uh
let me find the name of it really quick
I think it was Fink and woo and Warren
maybe
um but essentially they were trying to
figure out what strategy do people
actually use in this task so what they
did was simulate catching a Fly ball in
virtual reality
and the way that they got at it was
perturbed the trajectory of the ball in
virtual reality so it did something that
was physically impossible
but if you are canceling obstacle
acceleration then you'll still end up at
the Landing location if you are
predicting the trajectory you would end
up somewhere else potentially so that's
the kind of case where you you might
separate those two and and have
different predictions at a high level
about
what strategy an organism is using and I
also wanted to mention that you know I
don't want to rule out the the
possibility that
there is something like representation
and sort of you know turning like serial
processing that can happen in the brain
because this work falls into that first
kind of proof of concept location we
wanted to strip away as much as possible
and say how much kind of intelligence or
adaptive Behavior can you get with a
purely random Network that's kind of
dumb right
now I think there's a lot of ways in
which it's probably not very realistic
like a human brain
um that you know we have sort of
homogeneous Network structure in the
brain you're going to have different
lots of different sub Networks
those sub networks can do a lot of
things to the flow of information
through the network so you might have
for example a flow that you know moves
into a network and kind of gets you know
partially sent into some recurring Loop
that's like stored in some sub Network
and now that it could serve as a
representation that's available later to
some other system so I think you know
you could get a system like this to do
some of those things
and part of the point that I want to
emphasize is that
um you know even if you see those things
you you should be careful about taking
it literally
um because you can have a sort of
self-organized
Talons like system that just shifts into
these regimes and those regimes might
comp computationally or algorithmically
Implement something like a turing
machine so the point is to emphasize
that you know at the at the base what's
physically happening isn't necessarily
computation although you can get those
higher order things out of it and I
think that's a point that is you know
cognitive scientists often
get lost in talking about their models
and what is the model and what is
reality and so it's sort of a recurring
problem probably in in every field where
as you're writing a paper you start to
slip from one usage of a term to another
and you start to take it very literally
so
that's where we want to start is not
give people any chance try to read that
sort of Serial processing computational
architecture into this
cool in the pong example I thought of it
like a center fielder like that's doing
left right and then the classical lift
angle and the ball trajectory is really
on the should I move forward or
backwards
so you connect that wooden Walker with
the biomechanics
to pong playing Left Right and size of
the ball forward and backwards it's like
you're basically ready to be in the MLB
at that point if you can do that well
enough
yeah right right so yeah that's the
that's the interesting question is what
what would we have to do to this model
to get it to have you know near perfect
performance and
in this case we've gave it kind of an
easy situation where you know if you're
actually playing like the classic
version of pong it does a lot of
different things where the speed is
going to increase
um every time that you hit it and you
know maybe the angles of deflection are
changed in some way and here we just had
kind of elastic collisions and constant
speed and so it's pretty easy for the
you know a human would have no problem
with this and the network is only at
like 60 so
what kind of setup would you need to get
it to be perfect
um is something that I'll try to explore
in the future and you know maybe that
involves some kind of more modular
structure to the network
cool well one last thought and then a
last question you mentioned that just
because of trigonometry or Optics that
the optic flow is highest when the ball
is coming closest and I wonder if that
might relate to kind of critical slowing
of time or during pivotal action moments
a perceived slowing of time as a
homeostatic mechanism
for making sure that we can still act
adaptively and then when there's low
stimuli we Zone
because it's like we're having low yeah
flow and then when things are happening
like really fast you're you're Neo in
The Matrix then you have a critical
slowing that helps you negotiate that
right yeah that's that's really
interesting so I mean I know a little
bit about
critical slowing and just complex
systems
um and I haven't heard much about that
in terms of like time perception or like
the actual experience of it slowing so
that's really cool enough to check that
out but I think there there are
definitely some
um interesting relations here but what I
think is is most interesting about the
case where we turn off learning there
and it's still doing okay just because
of the laws of Optics I said I think
that's a great example of the gibsonian
point that there is structured
information in the environment so
without having any learning mechanisms
just by virtue of the way that Optics
changes with respect to movement you get
this this pattern of change where it's
more rapid when it's you know close to
you on the sides and it's slower when
it's in the middle and so there's
already some information there about
what you can do or what what's happening
in the environment that you don't have
to perform any computations to infer
that
and in this case I don't know if you
know not sure if we really see
critical slowing down in the network and
future steps for this will definitely be
to try to apply some more specific
dynamical systems or complex systems
methods to this to look for those
signatures and the Dynamics
um to me what it looks like is the
network kind of just freaks out it has a
seizure when it's about to miss the ball
everything starts spiking and it just
goes crazy and sometimes that craziness
is gonna make it move away from the ball
in which case it will miss but it was
about to miss it anyway in other cases
it'll move towards the ball just by
chance so you get sort of a 50 50 but
you're adding to your probability of
hitting in that case just by doing
something random
excellent well any final words or how
can people learn more or be involved
hear from from any of you
um who have interest on uh you know
working with me or just working with
this model or related stuff
um got a lot of ideas for what to do
next I'd like to do some kind of
evolutionary algorithms with this I'd
like to do some uh some kind of complex
systems analyzes of the Dynamics of the
network
um I'd like to kind of compare this to
data and most of all with some experts
in this community I think it would be
great to
that's those questions that we've been
talking about how do we do we see if
this fits with the active inference
approach or doesn't fit
um so if you have any interest in all in
any of that stuff reach out to me
um
uh my Twitter handle is at the beginning
and the end of the talks you can go back
in the video you can send me an email if
you Google my name you'll you'll get my
website and all of our code is up on OSF
open science foundations linked in the
paper
this is still a pre-print so I didn't
have a chance to clean out my code
before I uh put it up so hopefully not
too many of you are going to look at it
but before the final version goes up
I'll have a nice commented version and
it's pretty straightforward for anyone
who wants to use it to get started
thank you Ben
welcome back anytime and looking forward
to how this all continues
yeah thanks Daniel this was super fun
well talk to you later bye